Robert Di Domenica Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Music (Box 1-37)
  - Music by R. Di Domenica (Box 1-36)
    - Saeculum aurem, original ms., [(1967) for flute, piano and tape. Original manuscript with (row charts) (2 books plus pages for Movements II and III, also sketches for pre taped?)] (Box-folder 26/2)
    - Saeculum aurem, sketches and misc material, [see 26/2] (Box-folder 26/3)
    - Saeculum aurem, parts (2), [Solo flute part: 11 pages. Pre-taped flute part (8): 6 pages] (Box-folder 26/4)
    - Scarlet letter, orchestral score, final ms.: front matter and Act I, scenes 1-2, [(1986) an opera in three acts. Based on Nathaniel Hawthorne's The Scarlet Letter. Libretto by E. H. Elgin and Robert Di Domenica (in reality mostly done by me.) Orchestral score: 466 pages plus title page, "character" page, "orchestra" page, "scene" page. Final original manuscript (transparency)] (Box-folder 26/5)
    - Scarlet letter, orchestral score, final ms.: Act I, scenes 3-4, [see 26/5] (Box-folder 26/6)
    - Scarlet letter, orchestral score, final ms.: Act II, scenes 1-2, [see 26/5] (Box-folder 26/7)
    - Scarlet letter, orchestral score, final ms.: Act II, scene 2 (cont.), [see 26/5] (Box-folder 26/8)
    - Scarlet letter, orchestral score, final ms.: Act III, [see 26/5] (Box-folder 26/9)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 1 (Box-folder 27/1)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 2 (Box-folder 27/2)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 3 (Box-folder 27/3)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 4 (Box-folder 27/4)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 5 (Box-folder 27/5)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 6 (Box-folder 27/6)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 7 (Box-folder 28/1)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 8 (Box-folder 28/2)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 9 with laid in material (Box-folder 28/3)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 10 (Box-folder 28/4)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms: notebook 11 (Box-folder 28/5)
    - Scarlet letter, piano/vocal score: front matter and act I, [Final original manuscript (transparency) The Scarlet Letter, an opera in three acts based on Hawthorne's The Scarlet Letter. Libretto by E. H. Elgin and Robert Di Domenica (mostly done by me). (Piano)/vocal score (1987) by Robert and Leona Di Domenica. 260 pages plus title page, "character" page, "scene" page, tempo explanation page.] (Box-folder 29/1)
    - Scarlet letter, piano/vocal score: act II, [see 29/1] (Box-folder 29/2)
    - Scarlet letter, piano/vocal score: act III, [see 29/1] (Box-folder 29/3)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms.: notebook 1 (Box-folder 29/4)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms.: notebook 2 (Box-folder 29/5)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms.: notebook 3 (Box-folder 29/6)
    - Scarlet letter, original ms.: notebook 4 (Box-folder 29/7)
    - Scarlett letter, libretto, [My second opera. Although my friend, the poet, Gene Elgin (E. H. Elgin) is given credit for the libretto it is really by myself. The fact that he gave me a draft and that it remained in my mind eventually causing me to start the opera and then fashioning my own libretto (much in the same manner as The Balcony), all this caused me to give him credit] (Box-folder 29/8)
    - Sextet for woodwind quintet and piano, final ms., [(1957) final original manuscript (transparency) score: 29 pages] (Box-folder 30/1)
    - Sextet for woodwind quintet and piano, original ms. and additional material, [(1957) original manuscript (row sketches?)] (Box-folder 30/2)
    - Sextet for woodwind quintet and piano, parts, [Parts: flute, oboe, clarinet, horn and bassoon parts. Piano plays from score.] (Box-folder 30/3)
    - 16th century counterpoint, notebook 1 (Box-folder 30/4)
    - 16th century counterpoint, notebook 2 (Box-folder 30/5)
    - 16th century counterpoint, notebook 3 (Box-folder 30/6)
    - 16th century counterpoint, notebook 4 (Box-folder 30/7)
    - 16th century counterpoint, notebook 5 (Box-folder 30/8)
    - Sonata after essays, final ms., [(1977) (with soprano and baritone voice, flute and alto flute, and tape) final original manuscript (transparency) Score: 40 pages plus title page] (Box-folder 31/1)
    - Sonata after essays, original ms. and misc. material, [(1977) for piano, soprano, baritone, flute (and alto flute) and tape. Original manuscript (loose pages in envelope) (and 6 different rows used)] (Box-folder 31/2)
    - Sonata after essays, flute part, [flute/alto flute part: 2 pages] (Box-folder 31/3)
    - Sonata after essays, examples for lecture (text in 40/11), [Analysis examples: 5 pages. Tanglewood seminar "lecture": 32 pages (photocopy); leture given at Tanglewood Seminar on the composing of Sonata After Essays (an analytical diary)] (Box-folder 31/4)
    - Sonata after essays, bird calls, etc. and sketches, [Bird calls and sketches (in 2 notebooks)] (Box-folder 31/5)
    - Sonata after essays, sketches, [see 31/5] (Box-folder 31/6)
    - Sonata for alto saxophone and piano, final ms., [(1968) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) Score: 25 pages] (Box-folder 31/7)
    - Sonata for alto saxophone and piano, original ms. and misc. material, [(1968) original manuscript (row chart also on loose sheets)] (Box-folder 31/8)
    - Sonata for alto saxophone and piano, saxophone part, [saxophone part: 10 pages] (Box-folder 31/9)
    - Sonata for flute and piano, original ms. and misc. material, [(1957) original manuscript (and row chart)] (Box-folder 32/1)
    - Sonata for flute and piano, photocopy of final ms., [(1957) original transparency destroyed in preparing plates for publication (in my manuscript) by Edition Musicus. Enclosed is therefore a photocopy of my original transparency (score and flute part)] (Box-folder 32/2)
    - Sonata for flute and piano, photocopied flute part, [(1957) original transparency destroyed in preparing plates for publication (in my manuscript) by Edition Musicus. Enclosed is therefore a photocopy of my original transparency (score and flute part)] (Box-folder 32/3)
    - Sonata for flute and piano, published score and flute part (2 copies), [published score and part (my mother's copy) (published in my manuscript)] (Box-folder 32/4)
    - Sonata for piano, final score, [Final original manuscript (ink on transparency) (probably around 1955) The next to the last assignment done for Josef Schmid (followed by a sonata movement for string quartet). This work, unlike other student works was actually performed 2 or 3 times (by my wife Leonora Di Domenica). 16 pages] (Box-folder 32/5)
    - Sonata for piano, original ms., [One of the last exercises done with my Josef Schmid] (Box-folder 32/6)
    - Sonata for violin and piano, final ms., [(1966) final “original” manuscript (transparencies) (ink) Score copied by Donald Stewart: 35 pages] (Box-folder 32/7)
    - Sonata for violin and piano, original ms. and misc. material, [(1966) original manuscript (incomplete rows- inv. & ret. inv. only] (Box-folder 32/8)
    - Sonata for violin and piano, violin part, [violin part (movement I copied by Stewart, rest by me): 15 pages] (Box-folder 32/9)
    - Sonatina for piano (1954-1955), score, [Original ink on music paper manuscript (probably 1954 or 1955) Student work, one of the last assignments done for Josef Schmid. This proceeded studies in sonata allegro form. 8 pages plus title page] (Box-folder 32/10)
    - Sonatina for piano (1958), final ms., [(1958) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) 17 pages] (Box-folder 32/11)
    - Sonatina for piano (1958), original ms., [(1958) original manuscript (no row chart)] (Box-folder 32/12)
    - Sonatina for piano (1958), published score (2 copies), [actual publication- Edition Musicus] (Box-folder 32/13)
    - Songs from Twelfth night, final ms., [(1976) for tenor, flute, viola da gamba and harpsichord. 21 pages (including two different formats of Measure 65 to end. The single page solution is probably the intended one. Final original manuscript (transparency)] (Box-folder 32/14)
    - Songs from Twelfth night, original ms. and additional material, [(1976) original manuscript (1 book) (rows in loose sheets)] (Box-folder 32/15)
    - String quartet (1948), photocopied score, [Photocopy of work written before my 6 years of study with Josef Schmid] (Box-folder 32/16)
    - String quartet (1956), final score, [(1956) another study in sonata allegro form. Score and parts. This is the last assignment in my 6 years of study with Josef Schmid. All studies were done in a tonal language. The first work done after my study was Symphony (1956). This was still in tonal language, although extended in some movements approaching 12 tone. The Sonata for Flute and Piano (1957) is the first piece to be “actually” 12 tones and my works remained in this language from then on. Score: 18 pages. Parts: 6 pages each (2-3 facing if reproduced).] (Box-folder 32/17)
    - String quartet (1956), parts (4), [see 32/17] (Box-folder 32/18)
    - String quartet (1958), final ms., [(1958) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) 85 pages] (Box-folder 33/1)
    - String quartet (1960), original ms., [(1960) original manuscript (including revised notations for rondo)(no row chart)] (Box-folder 33/2)
    - String quartet (1960), revisions for rondo, [see 33/2] (Box-folder 33/3)
    - Symphony (1956), final ms., [(1956) final original manuscript (ink on transparency). 66 pages plus title page, plus instrumentation page. First work written after my 6 years of study with Josef Schmid. Never performed. I have always considered the next work (Sonata for Flute and Piano) to be my “opus 1" because of the musical language] (Box-folder 33/4)
    - Symphony (1956), second draft of original ms., [(1956) first work written after completing studies with Josef Schmid (student of Alban Berg) work dedicated to Schmid, never performed. Incomplete 1st draft and complete 2nd draft.] (Box-folder 33/5)
    - Symphony (1956), first draft of original ms. and misc. material, [see 33/5] (Box-folder 33/6)
    - Symphony (1961), final ms., [(1961) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) (12 x 17) Score: 48 pages: 48 pages (12x17) plus title page (11x14)] (Box-folder 34/1)
    - Symphony (1961), original ms., [(1961) original manuscript] (Box-folder 34/2)
    - Symphony (1961), photocopied parts (28), [(1961) All parts should have been printed with even numbered pages on left and odd on right. The following parts printed incorrectly (publisher error): piccolo, flute II, clarinet I, clarinet II, bassoon I, oboe I has pages 3 and 6 upside down] (Box-folder 34/3)
    - Symphony (1961), misc. material, [(1961) original manuscript (also rows, a page of sketches)] (Box-folder 34/4)
    - Symphony (1961), Mozart's Symphony No. 40--printed score, [a pocket score to Mozart’s G minor symphony- which my work is based on] (Box-folder 34/5)
    - Thema enigma, final ms., [(1985) (for flute) final original manuscript (transparency) 1 page. Written (along with other composers) for Gunther Schuller’s 60th birthday concert. It is solo tuba to his piece for tuba and chamber orchestra (Capriccio for Tuba and Chamber Orchestra--1960), which I used in my Variations in a Theme by Gunther Schuller (1983). The ‘requirement” was that they be 1 minute long (hence my♪=431⁄2)] (Box-folder 35/1)
    - Theme and variations for piano, score, [Original pencil (on music paper) manuscript (1953) Student work. One of the “assignments” done for my teacher Josef Schmid. I believe this proceeded studies in the rondo, sonatina, and sonata form. 29 pages] (Box-folder 35/2)
    - Trio for flute, bassoon, and piano, original ms., [(1966) original manuscript (and rows)] (Box-folder 35/3)
    - Trio for flute, bassoon, and piano, photocopied original ms., [(1966) photocopy of “original pencil manuscript” sent with first shipment. No “final” score was ever made. Score: 50 parts] (Box-folder 35/4)
    - Trio for flute, bassoon, and piano, misc. material (Box-folder 35/5)
    - Trio for woodwinds, photocopied score, [Photocopy of work written before my 6 years of study with Josef Schmid. I believe the Trio for Woodwinds was written while I was studying with Wallingford Riegger.] (Box-folder 35/6)
    - Variations on a theme by G. Schiller, final ms., [(1983) for solo tuba and chamber ensemble, final original manuscript (transparency) 42 pages plus title (instrumentation) page] (Box-folder 35/7)
    - Variations on a theme by G. Schiller, original ms. and misc. material, [(1983) for solo tuba and chamber ensemble, original manuscript (1 notebook) Schuller’s theme on a loose photocopy (in notebook) (and row chart)] (Box-folder 35/8)
    - Variations and soliloquies for orchestra, final ms., [(1988) final original manuscript (transparency) 123 pages plus title page and instrumentation page] (Box-folder 36/1)
    - Variations and soliloquies for orchestra, original ms.: notebook 1 with laid in material, [(1988) original manuscript (2 books and loose pages) (and row charts) also: program notes, Hamlet soliloquy, 9 page analysis (in book-1 loose)] (Box-folder 36/2)
    - Variations and soliloquies for orchestra, original ms.: notebook 2 with laid in material, [see 36/2] (Box-folder 36/3)
    - Variations and soliloquies for orchestra, misc. material, [see 36/2] (Box-folder 36/4)
    - Variations on a tonal theme, final ms., [(1961) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) 2 pages] (Box-folder 36/5)
    - Variations on a tonal theme, original ms., [(1961) original manuscript (no rows, but rows in score)] (Box-folder 36/6)
    - Variations on a tonal theme, published score, [(1961) actual publication- Edition Musicus] (Box-folder 36/7)
    - Violin sonata no. 1, photocopied score, [Photocopy of work written before my 6 years of study with Josef Schmid. I believe the Violin Sonata was written while I was studying with Wallingford Riegger.] (Box-folder 36/8)
    - Woodwind quintet, final ms., [(1963) final original manuscript (ink on transparency) 71 pages (alternate vocal ending added at the time of composition)] (Box-folder 36/9)
  - Music by Ellen Bender and Robert Di Domenica (Box 37)
    - Rappaccini's daughter, photocopied score, [Ellen Bender’s opera Rappaccini’s Daughter, based on Hawthorne’s story. Her first opera (in one act). Her score to her opera.] (Box-folder 37/1)
    - Rappaccini's daughter, libretto; photocopies of first and final drafts, [The libretto written by me. 1) my draft, 2) her final form] (Box-folder 37/2)
    - Misc. material (Box-folder 37/3)
  - Printed Music, [Leona Di Domenica believes these are pieces studied with her first piano teacher] (Box 37/4)
    - Emerson, De Witt G. The masters and their melodies Gossec, François Joseph. Gavotte in D Gurlitt, Cornelius. Album leaves for the young Haydn, Joseph. Sonata no. 2 Haydn, Joseph. Sonata no. 10 Mendelssohn, F. Praeludium Reinhold, Hugo. Miniaturbilder Scott, Cyril. Dansè negre Schytté, Ludvig. Witches' revels Swift, Newton E. Twelve children's pieces for piano
- Biographical Material (Box 38)
  The biographical folders contain some autobiographical material by Mr. Di Domenica. There are also various materials on his wife, Leona; his parents, Angelo and Philomena Di Domenica; and his in-laws, Henry and Beatrice Knopf.
  - Robert Di Domenica (Box-folder 38/1)
  - Leona Knopf Di Domenica (1) (Box-folder 38/2)
  - Leona Knopf Di Domenica (2) (Box-folder 38/3)
  - Angelo and Philomena Di Domenica (Box-folder 38/4)
  - Henry and Beatrice Knopf (Box-folder 38/5)
- Correspondence (Box 38-39)
  This is correspondence between Robert Di Domenica and his family, friends, and business associates, arranged alphabetically by the correspondent’s name. There is also a group of recommendations written for his students.
  - Babbitt, Milton (Box-folder 38/6)
  - Caldwell, Sarah (Box-folder 38/7)
  - Di Domenica, Leona (Box-folder 38/8)
  - Di Domenica, Philomena (Box-folder 38/9)
  - Dyer, Richard (Box-folder 38/10)
  - Edward B. Marks Music Corporation (Box-folder 38/11)
  - Feig & Taubman (Box-folder 38/12)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Foundation (Box-folder 38/13)
  - Kalban, Bernard (Box-folder 38/14)
  - New England Conservatory of Music (Box-folder 38/15)
  - Pfeiffer, Ellen (Box-folder 38/16)
  - Plymouth Philharmonic Orchestra (Box-folder 38/17)
  - Podlaha, Karl (Box-folder 38/18)
  - Rorem, Ned (Box-folder 38/19)
  - Rosica Colin Ltd. (Box-folder 38/20)
  - Schmid, Josef (1952-1959) (Box-folder 39/1)
  - Schmid, Josef (1960-1969) (Box-folder 39/2)
  - Schmid, Josef (no date) (Box-folder 39/3)
  - Schuller, Gunther (Box-folder 39/4)
  - Smith, Fenwick (Box-folder 39/5)
  - Taubman, Joseph (Box-folder 39/6)
  - Misc.: A-L (Box-folder 39/7)
  - Misc.: M-Z (Box-folder 39/8)
  - Recommendations: 1975-1982 (Box-folder 39/9)
  - Recommendations: 1983-1985 (Box-folder 39/10)
  - Recommendations: 1986-1988 (Box-folder 39/11)
  - Recommendations: 1989-1991 (Box-folder 39/12)
  - Recommendations: 1992-1994 (Box-folder 39/13)
  - Recommendations: 1995-1996 (Box-folder 39/14)
  - Recommendations: 1997-1998 (Box-folder 39/15)
  - Unidentified (Box-folder 39/16)
- Writings (Box 40)
  This is a group of writings by Robert Di Domenica, including analyses of several of his compositions. There are also writings by others, including student compositions.
  - Analysis of The Cenci Trilogy (Box-folder 40/1)
  - Analysis of Concerto Wind Quartet, Strings, and Timpani (Box-folder 40/2)
  - Analysis of Gone are the River and the Eagle (Box-folder 40/3)
  - Analysis of Variations and Soliloquies (Box-folder 40/4)
  - The esthetic and general philosophical attitudes of the major German Romantic composers (Box-folder 40/5)
  - Friends--past and present (Box-folder 40/6)
  - List of works that influenced me (I hope) (Box-folder 40/7)
  - Musical theory and composition in the college (Box-folder 40/8)
  - 60th birthday talk (Box-folder 40/9)
  - Some recordings I made as a flutist (Box-folder 40/10)
  - Sonata after essay (2 copies) (music in 31/4) (Box-folder 40/11)
  - Theory--composition (Box-folder 40/12)
  - Third stream (Box-folder 40/13)
  - Writings by others (Box-folder 40/14)
- Recording and Publications Material (Box 40)
  This is material relating to recordings in whose production Robert Di Domenica was involved. There is also a flyer from Edition Musicus, which published some of Robert Di Domenica’s music.
  - Material relating to Leona Di Domenica's recordings (Box-folder 40/15)
  - Material relating to GM Recordings (Box-folder 40/16)
  - Material relating to Edition Musicus (Box-folder 40/17)
- Teaching Material (Box 41)
  This is material relating to Robert Di Domenica’s career as an educator. Included are lesson plans, roll books, and student evaluations.
  - Lesson plans--Advanced harmony: 1986-87 (Box-folder 41/1)
  - Lesson plans--Advanced harmony: 1991-92 (Box-folder 41/2)
  - Lesson plans--18th and 19th century harmony/advanced harmony: 1989-90 (Box-folder 41/3)
  - Lesson plans--Tonal composition: 1986-87 (Box-folder 41/4)
  - Lesson plans--Tonal composition: 1991-92 (Box-folder 41/5)
  - Piano music (Box-folder 41/6)
  - Roll book: 1986-87 (Box-folder 41/7)
  - Roll book: 1989-1990 (Box-folder 41/8)
  - Student evaluations (Box-folder 41/9)
  - Material relating to the New England Conservatory of Music (Box-folder 41/10)
  - Material relating to Greenwich House Music School (Box-folder 41/11)
- Iconography (Box 42)
  This is a collection of photographs of Mr. Di Domenica, his relatives, friends and associates. There are some other photographs as well. There is also a folder containing a photocopy of a painting or drawing. This also includes a group of six oil paintings done by Mr. Di Domenica in his youth.
  - Paintings, (Done between the ages of 10-17, listed in approximate order of production with dimensions in inches.)
    - Mother and child (13x6)
    - Still life (27x27)
    - Two houses (35x39)
    - Still life with monkey and head (35x41)
    - Still life with table and vase (31x37)
    - Portrait of my mother (35x41)
  - Photographs (Box 42)
    - Robert Di Domenica (1) (Box-folder 42/1)
    - Robert Di Domenica (2) (Box-folder 42/2)
    - Leona Di Domenica and children (Box-folder 42/3)
    - Angelo and Philomena Di Domenica (Box-folder 42/4)
    - Di Domenica family: other members (Box-folder 42/5)
    - Friends and associates (Box-folder 42/6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 42/7)
  - Other (Box 42)
    - Photocopies (Box-folder 42/8)
- Clippings (Box 43)
  This is a group of newspaper and magazine clippings relating to Robert Di Domenica’s concerts, publications and recordings, as well as other materials. Within these three categories the material is arranged chronologically.
  - Concerts: 1948-1998, n. d. (Box-folder 43/1)
  - Publications and recordings: 1982-1985, n. d. (Box-folder 43/2)
  - Misc.: 1974-1998 (Box-folder 43/3)
- Programs (Box 43)
  This is a group of programs of performances involving Robert Di Domenica either as a composer or a performer, arranged chronologically.
  - 1948-1957 (Box-folder 43/4)
  - 1958-1975 (Box-folder 43/5)
  - 1976-1984 (Box-folder 43/6)
  - 1985-1990 (Box-folder 43/7)
  - 1991-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 43/8)
- Other Material (Box 43)
  This folder contains miscellaneous material such as a stock certificate and a short biography of Sarah Caldwell, mentioning her performance of Di Domenica’s work. There is also a group of photocopies of miscellaneous annotated envelopes.
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 43/9)